software engineering radio episode 81
interview with Erica
[Music]
hello listeners welcome to the Christmas
edition of software engineering radio
this one is another interview episode
with somebody who we've tried to get in
front of the microphone for a long time
and it never worked for the usual
reasons I didn't have time he didn't
have time we met at a conference and
well everybody had other stuff to do but
we now finally managed to do it a loop
slab 2007 in well where was it in
Montreal Canada
Welland we talked about what you would
expect about patterns about jae-hyun and
about eclipses about jazz should be an
interesting interview but before we get
to the content since this is the last
show of 2007 I just want to say thank
you for listening to SU radio for
supporting us with your positive
comments with your feedback and also
with your donations we have been running
this experiment well we tried to get
donations at a level that is enough for
us to be able to get some of the stuff
financed we want to finance and actually
the donations were quite okay I have to
find out exactly what the numbers are
and I will tell you early next year when
the 2007 year is really completely over
but it looks good I'm not yet sure
whether it's enough to so we can do it
without sponsoring the long term we've
also been given a significant amount of
money from a company and I'll reveal
details in the new year we have to say
thank you somehow and we'll do that
we'll put some stuff on the website and
maybe mention a company a couple of
times it's important for you to
understand that I didn't ask them it's
not like I asked for sponsoring they
just said hey we like as your radio here
is the money do something sensible and I
really think we should we should thank
them anyway so I will give you more
details beginning of next year this was
just a quick heads-up and since we're
talking about money things you might
have noticed on the SU radio website we
have created another button on the
basically on the title page on the left
so instead of giving us a one-time
donation you can also subscribe to se
radio with a monthly $3 subscription and
the nice thing about subscriptions is
that it gives you well it gives us I
should say a way of planning so if you
subscribe then we know that we probably
get such and such amounts of money per
month and that means we can plan ahead
so you might consider subscribing to the
regular donations there is another thing
I want to talk to about talk about I
have mentioned this in the past before
and that is that we were thinking about
a little su radio conference we are
tentatively calling it the se radio
get-together 2008 and well the
institutionalized coffee break we were
thinking about a open space conference
so on the SU radio website left side
more or less at the top you'll see a
nice picture of a campfire it says
something about su radio get together
please click there we have a couple of
questions where we need to know your
answers about how much when how long
which language and whether you're
interested in general so please go ahead
go there answer the questions this will
allow us to plan and decide whether
we're doing this or whether we're not
going to do this to be able to plan okay
that was enough of metadata let's get to
today's episode as I said it's an
interview with Eric gamma and well have
fun listening to it have a nice
Christmas tomorrow and the good 2008
talk to you in the new year
welcome Eric to show glad to be here so
Eric why don't you start by introducing
yourself to our audience so well my name
is Eric Emma I'm distinction engineer
working from Zurich we have a lab in
Zurich we have a small team there and
our current work focuses now beause
Eclipse and chess as you might call
later in the interview yeah it will
we'll cover these different things so
before we go there something I always
wanted to know where does your name
gonna come from it's actually quite
geeky so it's a good fit so is that
their typical name in Switzerland
the release attribute it's really a real
name it's so it's very popular in the
central part of Switzerland there's a
village where everybody is almost called
gamma okay so it's not that special
okay so let's first talk a little bit
about patterns everybody knows that
you've written this golf book together
with the other three guys so if you look
at look back at the influence the Gogh
book hair the patterns book hat are you
happy with how it went
what do you think how can it not be
happy well I don't know what I'm amazed
off looking at what has changed since
you wrote the book right he wrote the
book before internet before an hour
before XML before whatever right which
proved to me that people still
interested has some timeless material in
objects how they talk to each other
that's still in there so that's kind of
to me the most amazing thing however
there is also a lesson in there right
then which is Libby the frustration
maybe you cannot learn patterns from a
book and that the alternative is to not
have a book so her choice right between
having a book another book so of course
it has exceeded our wildest dreams
right so how many do you roughly sell
these days still is it this is still in
the charts kind of it's I still get a
check here I think we are north of
350,000 and we still sell cool thousand
per month so cool that's really
impressive and many companies know they
hand out the book to their employees
when they start the first day of working
so it's cool good idea actually to hand
out the book so what do you think about
the patterns community today how what do
you think how has it developed what's
your opinion in general about this stuff
so I first of all I think the the
chemical that has build around patterns
is is itself a success right some in a
circle I this idea of patterns and they
started early on in order to make a
success you build the community and I
think this was a very effective and I
think it's really a compliment also this
whole movement is that it's still alive
right so I was surprised here dupes law
there is still a tiny plop or how is a
company propagate off after the whole
model of
communication interaction shepherding
workshops but it's still alive and I
think there is now a whole new
generation and has in there and this
energizing the movement so I'm impressed
that it's it's still a life of course
the scope has protein yeah
as you see else when you look at the
Google for books on patterns you will be
impressed what's the scope is these days
but I think it's a very successful
community and the fresh the fresh minds
I think they keep the live and it's a
successful example also of rolling-over
community right so some people move step
down but new people came in and push it
forward and so I think it's great so
would you agree to the notion that let's
say that the basic design patterns are
all documented with your book and the
poster book and maybe two or three other
books or patterns and now things have to
become more domain-specific or
architectural specific and in order to
find more patterns I think that seven
able to pass you over see you right with
the coloration of this kind of each new
technology new experience comes new
lessons learned and you want to reuse
that experience that's why you should
capture impaired or impaired is a good
way to do that that's definite as I
wouldn't say that the whole hadn't
missed him is covered by by a buddy
design patterns book that but the core
was a good chair
come on so covers some less important
ones rights of my top 10 list of
patterns which are like in a book and
they're also ones which I don't like
that single thing of things one which I
think have overblown in the book we are
kind of almost it's it's a bad design
it's not are not objects right you have
one well-known thing to go would you put
dependency injection in there if you did
the book again today so actually we are
some reflection of two years ago if you
would modernize the book because there
people are right they complain the book
needs to be more nice no no doubt about
that
and we talk of what patterns will put in
right there is Stephanie nowhere type
object that comes in did he have some
representation that he can do gets a
little bit meta meta level
representation and all object this one
is one of them graphical mature dad and
dependency injection is such which i
think is also along the path of pattern
sinking or design pattern sinking my
designer pens is a lot about
abstract coupling we call determining if
you reference another type by an
interface and abstract class so it
depends injection makes it a coupling
even looser even extracting it out the
source code not have any kind of inject
it somewhere yeah making the into that
the connection somebody else's eight
responsibilities as late as possible so
and from that I think I would have to
think about how to write it up well but
I've seen Martin Fowler didn't attempt
so I think that's definitely something
the reason why I cover why I asked was
because I have heard several people that
said all the creational patterns in the
gogh book should basically go away we
can all do it with dependency injection
and I thought well that's not what I
would say now each pattern is about the
trade of yeah exactly and that was the
lesson else and you wrote the book right
initially we thought each patent is a
panacea
now then auntie sorry you said wait
you're wrong right for you to each
pattern comes trade of the obvious one
is additional indirection additional
complex and the same concert depends
injection right it has Christ
it has understanding problem you have to
understand how this 6/5 fits together
debugging issue and it will depends if a
single single factory method is to make
job for object creation that I'm fine so
you haven't been very active in the last
couple of years and the Paris Commune
haven't seen you on a parent's
conference was that intended or did you
just move on had other stuff to do no I
think it wasn't not intended but it's
just I I'm I still actively use patterns
or I'm interesting patterns I read the
plot proceeding which you had edited one
of them I guess yeah the property fire
to pull up t5 so I track it and I'm
interesting it and also I I use it when
I write about it remember that when I
wrote the eclipse book have from the
action point patterns which are yeah so
I I like to syncing patterns I have high
interest but just making active
contributions it has gone down yeah just
the focus yeah sure my work different no
intention it's not a loss of interest
although I've seen your name on the
editor board of advisory board or
program committee of the new patterns
journal that's about to come out from
the hills a group so I thought that was
good that's good and I that suppose I
also is a great opportunity to to get
back kind of to not lose touch happily
although although Utah joke that there
are only
people on the on the ball who haven't
done anything in patterns in the last
five years but we maybe shouldn't say
maybe that's a pattern for this okay so
let's move on to the next like thing
you're known for which is J unit and you
Jota just told me a couple of minutes
ago that today or this week is more or
less the 10-year anniversary anniversary
of J unit so why don't you tell us a
little bit about how J unit came about
okay it's kind of a fun story so exactly
ten years ago when I was in Atlanta and
Kent Beck was living in Zurich for two
years with his family and we flew
together with Austrian Airlines to
Atlanta and we had ten hours time and we
we not only like to talk to get a canted
i we also enjoyed programming together
and so that's as obvious it's great
opportunity he has had his idea about
his testing for amicus unit and kind of
I said okay I can teach you Java and if
you know as your has been lost small
talk yes you need okay that was cancer
story and I said okay I teach a job we
do it together and explain it together
and we talk patents patterns together
and it really happened during the flight
from Zurich that land that we wrote the
initial birth of the framework we were
drinking lots of almdudler and from then
on it has started and that's ten years
ago yeah so what you think that many
people say that j-unit is probably your
most pervasive contribution to the field
of software in general would you agree
or would you rob think that's maybe the
parent stuff I didn't make this up so I
just if I look at my sweat indication
factor oh yeah there's way more sweating
design patterns yeah James really now
it's a small fun little piece but isn't
that the nice thing about it it's small
it's easy to understand and it had this
huge impact now that's another community
success right yes
pattern was the community section is
also community success and of course
Kent did a really great job at that and
and I was glad I could count with you as
well so what is necessary to make
something the community success I mean
if we go on to two eclipses it's again a
community success so what is the secret
sauce here deceit there's our series you
have to get something to a level which
is interesting right it's it has
kind of a present mm-hmm but it has to
have enough interesting stuff ended that
others look at it okay it's not enough
to talk about some skits not enough to
talk about concepts it has to be around
a ball usable and then I guess you can
start build a community around it and of
course it needs not only code neat I
guess the test in fact that paper we
wrote the important which showed program
is actually it's uncool to not have
tests I wouldn't say all right it's cool
to have tests but it's uncool do not
have to that's maybe the thing to have
this much shift in mindset from testing
as a as something a chore that you have
to do and that's kind of boring and dull
to something that is the drive of all
the design of your system absolutely and
I can't imagine I want to go back right
to the before test you know that's where
programming your test sensitive to
intense program it's interesting you
should say this word because I I mean
test-driven development is about writing
the test first you said something
different you said test aware or test
sensitive are you actually like one of
these let's say religious fanatics let's
say you always have to write the test
first or are you a bit more pragmatic
there to say the important point is you
have the coverage it doesn't matter if
you do it first right I think the
important thing is you have to test and
sometimes it's good to write me in
advance I think it's almost always good
to help me advance but yeah I think I'm
pragmatic now I'm happy when I have
tests learned when it happened I don't
don't dump or not that much well the
argument is always if you write tests
then you know sure it makes your
software test the ball and that's a good
thing if you think about dependency I
think about setting up the objects as
old that's all good things and it will
not downplay no no see I had I meant
through like I mean I got the best test
education right with pair programming
with Ken yes and trust me when I start a
program want to implant some code
feature in framework without writing a
test first he would have pulled away the
keyboard from immediately instead and I
think it's a great experience and I also
guess that if you want to introduce
testing into a community you have to be
radical in some sense and always do it
in a certain way if you say that Ken
would pull the keyboard away you have to
be really
consequent and then once it's in you you
can then make the compromises absolutely
absolutely
I think now it's Kent's mind cities
which I start appreciate if something is
good turn the volume to the maximum and
that's how you get and make no
compromise right okay let's look at
another thing you've been involved in
obviously eclipse so well I mean we can
talk quite a bit about eclipses what
would you say is is the most important
aspect of eclipses maybe except from the
obvious which is the community so back
again so what is the technical what's
the important technical aspect of
eclipses that make that can make it so
successful as it is these days I think
it's it's maybe two things right first
of all from the beginning we had this
kind of growth path in mind how we won't
extend the Eclipse no no no Fred Brooks
made this some point of the group when
you design a system keep the gross pass
after system in mind and see how it
captured well we had limited eclipse
from the beginning said everything
should be plug-ins yeah but you also
understood it needs to have a growth
path because if you're successful there
will be tons of plugins yeah so we had
this kind of modularity plus scalability
in mind from the beginning that's right
it is this Taric declarative plugin
dependency is modeled with extension
points which lazy load dependencies
things like that so that's the key thing
right keeping the Groves path of eclipse
in mind modularity is a very important
lesson in other words maybe it has an
architecture that is able to cope with
unexpected or unplanned extensions I
would say it's planned for growth and
component but unplanned expect extension
smells to me too much like uncontrolled
extension you're uncontrolled extension
it turns out to often be a problem
because maintainability device and
that's the other thing which was
important Eclipse it's not only that the
gross past but also the stability you
write in mind because if you want to get
growth right you have to get some stable
foundation that things can grow on top
yeah as much as I hate as a develop the
API stability and constraints you have
there it's it's hat it's like you're
getting handcuffed and I have to be
build layers and
years of compatibility now I think we
have five different preference
mechanisms and I don't know actually if
you make a test on me I'm sure I would
not be able to tell you which one is
implement in top but that surprise you
pay right for growing community you have
to have a gross modularity story and the
stability story plus whatever God we had
also the tools story I think that was
like what do you mean by the tool story
it's good if you buy architecture you
allow that you can have a gross past
three Canada for ditional plugins but
you should also make it easy that 200
new plug assurance so that's why we have
not only the clips comes with a million
a nice child album tool but also comes a
toolset for writing plug-in right
managing plugins and so on right so it's
kind of these three things which which
gives the snowball effect you enable the
growth paths things happen and and more
more plugins coming to place more and
more people know about plugins and then
you have the skills no and that was
really key and I really stopped counting
right I have no numbers lemons
how many plugins sell flavors or how
many things it's just has it has escaped
me couple of years I always like to call
it clips an operating system for tool
development that was it the beginning
division until he got abused for normal
application development like RCP over
RCP rich client rights era where they
call this abused Noah
however in South the development when it
comes to shape something right one key
element versus focus focus and we know
yes we could have built a general
framework for for building applications
and we said no we folks and tools
platform that's what he want
hmm and then from the outside came to
request can you actually had depth on
that as he abused and it was really
pressured right because they had to
start to hack a clip sent and then so
that's not good and actually we see
potential and we were kind of surprised
what generality of tomorrow mark which
really yeah given our focus wasn't
anticipated and now it even moves to the
server right and now do you move the
server and so it's a West GI and
extensive building model everywhere and
as we've all seen chance right we
leverage this extensibility also on the
server so you said that stability
is obviously a key component of making
an architectural future-proof so people
can trust that what they do now isn't
gonna be you know like rubbish tomorrow
so what do you do technically and later
we discuss about the process what do you
do technically to to keep the Eclipse
core and the existing plugins API stable
okay what we invest into right now is
API tools mmm
we always had kind of tools which just
compared API so we know whether we
haven't broken something yeah all right
so we have tools that give us a diff
from from an API stuff and I'm proving
that right now we also have I guess
since Eclipse 3 we have support that you
know when you're not using API called
garbage collection kind of it tells you
what was never used no no no you want to
educate your clients what they should
program again but ok so that's why you
make explicit what is a poor not yeah
and with tools we have in Eclipse
since Eclipse 3 you can say you know and
see whether you use a method which is
not the other way around yeah I said
that's kind of the other thing which
helps us know because if if our
community doesn't understand the value
of api's and the programming its
internal it don't give us feedback when
they have to use internal stuff and ask
because that's a sign we should expose
more and the records you intentionally
we start we start with a small set of
exposed API is because we know the
commitment is serious so that's why your
other do it on demand by request so
let's briefly look at the development
process you've given tons of talks and
shown the same slide so many times so
wait which slide are you referring to I
don't remember all of them specifically
I was just getting at the point that you
really you have you as a team have
realized that the way you develop
software is probably not the worst way
because you're able to deliver stable
reliable stuff in regular time intervals
so that's why you've started documenting
and quote formalizing the Eclipse way
which is the process of developing
eclipse itself so can you talk a little
bit about that what can people learn
from Eclipse development and I guess
except test-driven development I assume
that's part of it if you look at the
Eclipse practices VB use
we are part of the Eclipse way many of
them are established agile practice
right right continuous integration
continuous testing iterative development
we haven't innovated there at all right
have we tried out what worked for us we
keep doing so we try pair programming
didn't stick we sometimes use it but I
would say no the value I see is the set
of practices we use and how we evolve it
over time mm-hm
you know by retrospectives have improved
it and I think what people can learn
from that is more also how agility can
scale rightly attributed T and again the
key element here is now well Weaver key
components assign a team to component
and then agree overall across component
on our rhythm the iterative development
and each iteration has and will be
iterative but also have added value so
iterative plus incremental the obvious
buzzword and that enables feedback all
right and then the next key lessons the
transparency right so transparency is a
good thing for self-development and
that's not just towards the outside it's
also transparency within the teams
everyone else are aware it does key
point is that guys at some point when
you start to use the same communication
infrastructure inside as outside yes
because then it helps you in the inside
also but it also enables outside of the
car you feedback yeah I think another
another key topic is the fact that
you're actually developing the develop
developing a development tool so you can
eat your own dog food you can use the
tool to develop the tool so people have
to use what they did before right right
eat your own dog food drink your own
champagne that's a benefit it definitely
does something which others don't have
is a luxury right others have applied
the Klipsch way as well and the feedback
was know many of the practices applying
easily know how we do approvals I knows
whatever that works well that's of
course the eat your own dog food which
is kind of special because we build our
own tool right the other thing is kind
of some platform specific practices that
we come a build tool ask the API focus
which doesn't apply to all the orders
but uh
so I've seen experience reports from
others using Eclipse way and it show me
at it's it's it's it's a good set of
agile practices and its first well to
make and and its publicly documented so
we can put a link in the show notes I
guess yeah
so let's draw an analogy in the same way
maybe it's a bit of a stretch but anyway
so in the same way as at some point you
and Kent decided to codify or build a
tool that helps you do the test-driven
development which would be j-unit you
also not took the Eclipse way and
codified that into a tool that helps you
do distributed agile development which
leads us to jazz although you don't like
jazz I was told I don't like jazz music
you like the chest project so in a way I
think jazz again was driven by different
influences and obviously the Eclipse
influence was was was big right we
learned a lot from Eclipse first of all
I mentioned this transparency I
mentioned the practices we do and how we
can actually get more to support with
these practices so exactly you want to
kind of support the Eclipse way by jazz
the toolset however it's obviously we
don't want to limit chest just to the
clips way right so it's why the way we
do that is kind of you have some process
awareness in the kernel and you can plug
in different processes it little process
framework thing right know the clips
process framing could be used mostly for
that is describing or process okay this
is a good framework for describing tasks
the input you have and and what you
should consider when you do that what
our practices for that I really like
practice it's kind of a sticky things no
no no too much the task so the Kosovo's
frame fits into it for us there's this
we call the static proces description
right okay one resu yeah but we are more
interested from a tool siding to enacted
one right if you look at our team does
right there's so many steps they have to
be aware of when you deliver change to
the team right so then you have to
copyright stuff you have sometimes need
a review and this is the thing which you
want to enact right which is kind of a
more interesting because this gives more
value right because reading what they
were likes to read but if you get guided
and get assisting to do the boring
tedious steps that was kind of the idea
and of course you don't want to
constrain isn't limited to the clips way
that's why we say I said the process is
pluggable you can plug in the clips
where you can plug in other process
which can influence how jazz behaves
depending
can you give us like an insight into a
number of it's a cool innovative
features that chess provides I mean if
people saw the demo or some of the
videos we'll put links into it they can
see live how things work I can you give
us like three or four really nice
convincing things that maybe other tools
can't do the challenge here is and when
it comes to team development team
support it's not like with IDs IDs where
it's just a single feature like a
refactoring or quick fixes right or
support for fixing problems it's many
little things that help you to be more
effective hmm so that's why no I can't
name you just one or two features I
can't just more say what are our key
focus address we have laughs right so
key key themes are whatever we do we
want to put the team in the center all
right what does a team how can you make
the team more effective we can do that
no way I'm having the tools know about
the team structure know about team roles
our team responsibilities and team
process so the team first sang shows was
a key theme which i think is a really
distinctive feature right you can see
what happens in a team you can RSS feed
from a team teams can have their own
continuous build and they are associated
with the team are cool when you can
invite it into a team right you get set
up and each team can also customize the
process very important right those kind
of real team focus we understand and not
every team is the same right as it was a
key lesson also my clips right I mean
although they're doing SWT is totally
different
then we answer if I need Java
development so then there are kind of
two levels in ingest one is the team as
the smallest entity except for the
developer himself and then there is
maybe this bigger thing which is a
collection of teams that collaborate on
the team's very teams exactly so that's
then the next thing right you have teams
and tools note teams and their
relationship and the artifacts are home
then you can you have mechanism to scale
up the teams of learners and that's I
guess the brings us ended at a point
where a key thing of chess is you have
tightly integrated tools right you have
tools which allow us to answer questions
which are hard to answer if you have
them isolate or pointer tools you know
is to fix
in the build or things like that which
you can just reach information from the
build system point buckling system can
collect stuff manually but you have it
in one place so into third thing is
scheme that we have all these tools
working together right we get
information about progress and artifacts
that you wouldn't get otherwise because
you can give it in a health information
project in for information which and
again helps on the transparency so it's
kind of Somerset holidays three singer
team is in the center then the process
awareness that tool really has process
baked in the bottom because I'm process
it really if you don't have in the in
bottom it's hard to bolt it on Tariq
unless you try to do this aspect and
whatever technologies which we know very
powerful but have other trade-offs and
that's why we we won't have it in the
core and then the third is we collect
data about that team is doing make it
available which improves transparency by
having one just one feature I saw at
some point was quite nice that you if
you if you fix it back in a certain
environment you can make the environment
persistent with the box if somebody else
wants to work with that bug he can
basically get the workspace that that's
completely settled laying so yes all the
environment management crap that you
have to go through seems to be gone I
think you know if you look at I'm great
as I'm with today's development tools I
feel I'm great with with program right I
have refactoring fixes all the tedious
stuff is is gone by the end when it and
when I leave my sandbox and I start to
interact with the team yeah then it's
very boring stuff and that's what you
want address with jazz not when you want
to reproduce the state of a new
workspace with the failure in the build
right we just have this information
captured you have a snapshot and you can
say okay from the snapshot trade my
workspace it matches there so it's jazz
only for distributed team source they're
also absolutely not no I the way I was
headed now jazz is actually scaled up to
distributed teams we use it ourselves
since 11 months we do all our chest
stuff with chess but I would start to
use it actually create a one developer I
will start use just easy this because
you want to collaborate you want
exchange stuff you wanna tracks
you will soon have a need for a build
you want to share code so rated in one I
would start use jazz now chess can
really scale down yeah so what do I have
to do to use jazz is the commercial is
it open source so or is it released yet
we have a better program so you can
register on chester net right get a
registration we want to have a more
gradual approach now to to make it
available it's not open source it's
right now we see there will be a
commercial product next year the name of
course I might dress as the code name
it's not genuine a chance is kind of
more than name of the technology ok
write the product there will be prosper
than the top of the chest semi sit
Eclipse right eclipse in Atlanta for
mules my products Billy on top of it and
we will bundle the first thing which we
will have note the cooperation support
build a source control Bach tracking
you've got your own version control
system and it's you have different
integration approaches as I said tight
integration with record for us so that's
why f3 actually it's sensitive here we
have three errors and see kind of
integrations right we have our own yeah
which gives it a tight and deep
integration then we have kind of what we
call more and coexistence so when you
have subversion right so not everybody
wants to jump on our only understand so
we have kind of a easy you can import
from subversion or you can just get a
looser integration at subversion and
then the third level is what we call
connectors which gives us a bridge to an
existing source control system exactly
in particular the ones we have the
rational clearcase right so we have a
connector to click isn't ideas and we
can synchronize it a module hood SCM you
can own so a team could work in chess
and synchronize with a model hood from
time to time like more releases so day
to day is that wasn't okay so this kind
of also shows different integration lies
we have to support okay so let's let's
finish up this chest discussion with the
question of how it relates to eclipse
it's obviously built on topic on top of
Eclipse and you already said that it's
gonna be a commercial product will parts
of it all the technology will that go it
some of it go to eclipse
you're right now we we leverage Eclipse
heavily on both the client and the
server and even our web infrastructure
is using
the Eclipse modularity OSGi support to
get extensibility we have of course
leveraged eclipse experience you have
built on that as well and the question
about open sourcing parts of it so we
will we have announced we consider open
sourcing parts of the infrastructure
it's just kind of for us an interesting
challenge now where to draw the line
yeah and given that this challenge is so
long it takes us longer to fix it but
it's still intent that we open-source
part of universe structure and very open
services that's still open right right
now we have our comedians a stone that
mm-hmm that's where you have a current
it like when we started Eclipse right
you have news groups and mailing lists
whatever you want yeah okay okay let's
look at to three topics that are not
directly related to these things before
we close this episode one is that I mean
you're obviously quite experienced in
building tools for languages you've done
the Java IDE part of Eclipse I think
that was your responsibility
I was original team Lee I agent Lee dr.
Cho that want to write it yeah and now
you've moved on to eclipse other people
do that now I guess that's what I
understand
no no no that's not okay no eclipse you
still need to have a heart right so a
quarter of the Delhomme some developers
have moved the clips but it's lots of
horsepower
okay stealing I mean you personally from
yes that's what I'm focusing on chess
but it's not you know that all the clips
develop no no no in a mighty move of
chess dear our heart and in my lab in
Zurich right is about him have team is
working to clear I have this work out
Jeff okay so what I wanted to try to get
it was the fact that well we all know
this this hype on dynamic language is
why I shouldn't call it hype I mean
there is serious stuff in it so what do
you think from a tool builders
perspective is it really the type the
static typing that makes tools like
eclipse possible or do you think that
it's just harder to build good tools for
dynamic languages and they will show up
at some point no I I think it's totally
possible but the problem is now you have
so many different of these dynamic
languages I never looked at all our
investment you have to build into JDT
right and that sets the bar yes and the
challenge is really no for
all the other languages get to the
similar bar and the right thing to do
there I think isn't that's what the odds
are already seeing happening now will
you build some common infrastructure
yeah like a diamond dynamic language
toolkit or whatever scope which the
exact exactly tries to do that and many
things you can do for them clang shoes
as well well of course the mists of
state of static type information
restricts the amount of searching and
things you can do but a refactoring you
can't do this if you know of what the
type of something is you can't
don't forget ant refactoring starting
small talk right that is interesting yes
yeah oh yeah and their ways either way
you know by looking what's in the
message what's in the catalogs which
messages are available whatever is and
you can do things just a bit more
complicated because you don't have this
type tag you actually have to understand
what's happening what happens but I
think you know that's the thing we
should not forget Smalltalk had a very
good idea in the head refactoring so
it's a dynamic language self is not the
dynamic language at a very good IDE so
we should not use it as an excuse for
not being ambitious right that's
actually know that you talk about it I
think that one reason why self and
Smalltalk could do it is because it was
a self reflective system so the the IDE
worked basically in the same let's call
it VM for the sake of the argument as
the thing and for example in Ruby as far
as I understand that's not the case it's
not a repository VM based thing you have
no what I'm trying to get it if you have
reflection and and can do all these
things dynamically as opposed to just
having let's say text that you have to
analyze it's probably a different world
maybe that's interesting to write the
meta information right and of course in
small ticket just had it there you
literally ask the object what can I do
exactly have you seen our refactoring
tools for emerging I guess there's it
was supposed to Atlanta right yeah true
it'll samel are just doing something in
the area so and I think we should
continue being ambitious know even there
and dynamic languages have to play so
it's important like javascript is very
important do you have a very good child
script one thing that that you also
mentioned in passing was one reason why
we have these great tools for Java
development is also because for a couple
of years I have I think
time is over that was only one language
I was Java so everybody invested into
that now that we have maybe a bit more
diversity again maybe there is not as
much as much money going into each of
those so maybe we shouldn't expect will
to be that great anymore we were never
in the in the luxury position to work
with on technology a self develops I
think someone right you always had XML
we always had HTML whatever so I think
single language that's 10 years ago
right so we work with multiple language
mobile technologies and some point that
we get nice integration when our also
between the languages refactoring and
then I do rename that the spring
description a factory reference to a
class it's also update not all the
things which is I guess another
challenge you have in a tool space right
now yeah there's also some yeah where I
work in this modeling environment we
want to change a model element and that
also also changes the name of a class
you generated from it or the other way
around and so this kind of stuff that's
why also in Eclipse you're invested in
refactoring participation testing
framework we can plug-in literally okay
so let's wrap this episode up with a
last question you've done quite a bit of
work in all kinds of areas in software
engineering what is your opinion about
what's really the important
characteristics a software engineer
should have what should people invest in
when they try to make themselves better
I think a passion for programming yeah
that helps always there right so that's
you should not feel good if you haven't
programmed since a while so I think this
passion has to be there and that's very
important right our stuff is moving so
fast so make yourself a test have you
read the book in the last two months
have you read the new book have you
learned the new language in the last
year so continuous learning obviously is
the obvious thing and I think it's the
fact that you have so many open source
projects now no there is such a wealth
of stuff to learn from size increase the
best way to learn is know look into open
source approach Excel how they do stuff
you learn a process you learn
interesting no development techniques or
ever so it's really continuous learning
and so what was the last language you
flipped into just out of curiosity so I
I bought
I'm looking at about a long book aku I
bought it when I read it all right oh
good ahead of me okay Eric thank you
very much for being on the show and well
thanks glad to be here
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details